github.com/amyxlu

amyxlu@cs.toronto.edu +1-647-968-6833 linkedin.com/in/amyxlu

Summary

I am a graduate student at the University of Toronto/Vector Institute for AI. I am interested in **developing** biologically-principled machine learning methods, with an emphasis on self-supervised representation learning, generalizability, and biological interpretability. I also serve on Research to the People, which organizes research collaborations of genomics/ML researchers for patients of understudied diseases.

EDUCATION

• University of Waterloo
Bachelors of Science, Honours Science, Bioinformatics Option

Waterloo, Canada
2014 - 2019

University of Toronto, Vector Institute

Master's in Computer Science

Stanford University

Visiting Student, Departments of Computer Science and Genetics

Toronto, Canada Jan 2019 – Present

Palo Alto, USA Sept 2019 – Dec 2019

EXPERIENCE

Stanford University

Visiting Student Researcher — Domain Adaptation in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Anshul Kundaje

Palo Alto, USA 2019 - Present

• Domain adaptation, ChIP-seq data, interpretability: Using domain adaptation methods to improve transcription factor binding prediction when evaluating for a different cell line.

University of Toronto/Vector Institute

Toronto, Canada

Masters Student — Representation learning in genomics, Dr. Alan Moses & Dr. Marzyeh Ghassemi 2019 – Present

- Self-supervised learning, natural language processing: Adapting attention-based NLP models to learn self-supervised representations of protein sequences.
- Generalizability, computer vision: Benchmarked self-supervised and canonical computer vision methods in a microscopy image dataset with covariate shift to highlight generalization failures in machine learning. (NeurIPS 2019; ICML 2019 Self-Supervised Learning Workshop)
- Algorithmic fairness, clinical decision support: Quantitative and qualitative evaluation of bias in "black box" contextual word embeddings on clinical notes. Explored debiasing methods using adversarial gradient-reversal. (NeurIPS 2019 Workshop for ML for Healthcare, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML.)

Harvard Medical School/Boston Children's Hospital

Boston, USA

Research Intern — Machine Learning in Clinical Genomics, Dr. Piotr Sliz

2018 - 2019

- Genotype-phenotype studies, clinical interpretability: Understanding disease genotype-phenotype relationships using machine learning models. Interpreted important model features to seek novel disease-associated variants from whole exome (WES) data.
- Variant filtering, pathway analyses: Applied standard filtering pipelines for false-positive variants. Explored classification from pathway- and variant-level features.
- Machine learning, dimensionality reduction: Explored methods for capturing epistatic non-linearities and statistical dimensionality reduction.

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

Undergraduate Thesis Student — Deep Learning in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Andrew Doxey

2017 - 2018

- Convolutional neural networks in genomics: Implemented a convolutional neural network which classifies ATAC-seq accessibile regions with 91% accuracy.
- Interpretability: Interpreted the neural network by reconstructing the first-layer feature map as position-weighted matrix (PWM) motif. All motifs found statistical matches in JASPAR, a database of known motifs.
- Phylogenetics, metagenomic data mining: Used various bioinformatics pipeline tools (HMMER, BLAST, etc.) to understand biochemical properties of potentially uncharacterized toxins in metagenomic data.
- Self-directed learning: Self-learned deep learning concepts and Python as a biology student.

École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Research Intern — Molecular Dynamics Simulations, Dr. Matteo Dal Parero

Lausanne, Switzerland 2017

- Molecular dynamics: Used molecular dynamics (MD) and GROMACS to simulate enzyme-membrane mechanisms of bacterial "superbugs".
- Workflow automation: Analyzed and automated simulations using R, tcl/tk, and Csh scripts.

University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

Research Intern — Data Visualization in Pharmacoepidemiology, Dr. Suzanne Cadarette

2015 - 2017

• Data visualization, pharmacoepidemiology: Used R to visualize the social diffusion of methodological innovation. Contributed to two co-authored publications and an international epidemiology conference.

Awards

- NSERC Canada Graduate Scholarships-Master's (CGS-M) Award: NSERC federal research grant. Valued at \$17,500.
- NSERC Michael Smith Foreign Supplement: Supports high-calibre Canadian graduate students in pursuing research abroad. Valued at \$6,000.
- Scholarship of Excellence in Research: One of 13 students sponsored for research at EPFL. Valued at CHF 4,500.
- University of Waterloo: Various entrance awards totaling \$6,000.
- Associate of The Royal Conservatory (ARCT): Performer's Diploma in Piano.

Publications and Conference Proceedings

- Published: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Schormann W, Ghassemi M, Andrews DW, Moses AM. The Cells Out of Sample (COOS) dataset and benchmarks for measuring out-of-sample generalization of image classifiers. *Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2019.*
- Submitted: Zhang H*, Lu AX*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. *Equal contribution.
- Presented: Moses A, Lu AX, Lu AXP, Ghassemi M. Transfer Learning vs. Batch Effects: what can we expect from neural networks in computational biology? *Machine Learning for Computational Biology (MLCB) 2019*.
- Published: Ban J, Tadrous M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Cadarette SM. Diffusion of indirect comparison meta-analytic methods to study drugs: a systematic review and co-authorship network analysis. *BMJ Open*.
- Under revision: Consiglio GP, Maclure M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Ban JK, McCarthy L, Cadarette SM. Guidance documents for the application of Self-controlled Crossover Observational PharmacoEpidemiology (SCOPE) designs are needed: systematic review and animated co-authorship networks. Submitted to Pharmacoepi Drug Saf.

Workshop Papers and Posters

- Presented: Lu AX*, Zhang H*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Poster presentation, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health. *Equal contribution.
- Presented: Zhang H*, Lu AX*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Extended Abstract, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Machine Learning for Healthcare. *Equal contribution.
- Presented: Abdalla M, Zhang H, Lu AX, Chen I, Ghassemi M. Quantifying Fairness in a Multi-Group Setting and its Impact in the Clinical Setting. Poster presentation, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health.
- Presented: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. Paired Cell Inpainting: A Multiple-Instance Extension of Self-Supervised Learning for Bioimage Analysis. *Poster presentation, ICML 2019 Workshop on Self-Supervised Learning.*
- Presented: Lu AX, Rockowitz S, Poduri A, Sliz P. From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. *Poster. Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019*.
- Submitted: Lu AX, Tam ES. Effect of prophylactic brimonidine on subconjunctival hemorrhage in laser-assisted cataract surgery. *Poster abstract*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Consiglio GP, Cadarette SM. Dynamic Visualization in Co-Authorship Network Analysis. Poster presentation. Leslie Dan Faculty of Pharmacy Undergraduate Research Symposium.
- Presented: McIlroy-Young R, Lu AX, Guenther N, Olarnyk A. A Network Analysis: Did the Arab Spring Impact the Academic Network of Tunisia Between 2010 and 2015? Poster presentation. Knowledge Integration Symposium.

SERVICE AND ACTIVITIES

- Research to the People (formerly SVAI): Core Team of Research to the People, a non-profit connecting patients of rare genomic diseases to the medical/AI research community and industry partners through collaborative research initiatives.
- Residence Don: Organized events and established rapport with diverse students. Responded to mental health and conduct crises. Leader for the Velocity Residence, a spin-off for the Velocity start-up incubator.
- Tosamaganga Hospital, Tanzania: Supported operations at a rural Tanzanian hospital and shadowed surgical procedures. Expenses were covered by scholarships, fundraising, and part-time tutoring.

Teaching

- Teaching Assistant, Genetics: Taught weekly tutorial lectures for BIOL 239 at the University of Waterloo.
- Piano, music theory: Taught piano performance (up to RCM 7), ear training, RCM music history, and RCM Intermediate Rudiments.
- Tutoring: Tutor for IB Math and IB Chemistry.

Talks

- Vector NLP Talks: Quantifying and Removing Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Co-presenter.
- Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019: From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. *Lightning talk*.

SELECTED HACKATHON PROJECTS

- Chatsense: Mobile chat app using a sentiment analysis machine learning API on voice messages and mapping dominant emotions to emojis, designed for the autism community. Team project. "Can a Computer Hear How You Feel?" prize: YHacks at Yale.
- Alice: Web login page using a trained facial recognition model to login to online banking without passwords, designed for dementia patients. *Team project. Desjardin prize: ConUHacks III.*